[Music]
[Applause]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio net SC radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio was brought to you by I Triple
E software magazine online at computer
or / software so I'm sitting here in the
energy office in Berlin with Martin
Buser for a car Martin hello Martin is
soft across French and has been involved
with because a child in Java events in
in Europe so he has been part of an ale
Socrates and go TOCOM he also co-founded
closer brothers for de and IT concerns
he runs with his brother
Yaroslav he while this mainly concerned
or interested in software quality and
well tested code and likes to share best
practices from proving good quality and
one of the ways how you can improve code
quality and actually make that practical
and you know also to learn about testing
is cultural traits so that is what we
are going to talk about today the first
question obviously is so what is the
code retreat
yeah well the short answer it's a day of
training so it goes from let's say 9:00
to 5:00 and you called all the time with
a lot of different people can you talk a
little bit more about the structure so
what is it that you actually develop in
such a code retreat I mean um
the focuses that we want to improve our
skill set therefore we need to Nexus
Isis in vehicle and for this we are
using the comic game of life and we do
six sessions we start with the session
and during the session the attendees try
to implement the game they start from
scratch and they try to actually get
finished but this is not the point in it
so we don't want to deliver anything we
want to explore different solutions ok
maybe we should talk a little bit more
about the game of life so I mean maybe
you want to explain it I guess you you
explained it quite a lot of times during
the
retreats yes this is like really easy so
you have cells in an infinite universe
and depending on certain rules itself a
born die or are born and on their legs
sweet for you or rules depending how you
phrase them and basically the the
universe is ticking and every take you
apply these rules to all cells and they
decide this are going to live for the
next generation or going to die on users
are born let me add something because I
find quite interesting and I guess we
will also provide some links in the in
the notes so the interesting thing about
it is that this simple games actually
turing-complete so you can do any
calculation in that game so it's it's
very interesting thing give from
theoretical computer science yes they
are actually game of life in game of
life that's mechanized video on YouTube
well so we have the cells and they are a
two-dimensional grid you know so every
cell has eight neighbors and this is how
we start so this is like a exercise and
in doing this six sessions we try
different approaches to work on it and
also have different constraints for
every sessions because well there is a
facilitator who is like leading this
exercise on this home coverage read and
he's guiding that participant in a
certain direction as you said it's done
multiple times so how do you do it I
mean is it just let you say okay a
police implement game of life and that's
it or is there any more guidance that
you give it you said that the goal is
not to actually implement game of life
it's more about making the participants
better developers so how do you achieve
that how do you guide them to become
better pro developers during those coach
retreats I mean there are obviously some
things which don't work and soft so I
think everybody can think about the
project he was involved in then if you
look back and see how bad they have been
tested or how bad the names were um but
it was to extend these projects or
understand what is going on and we are
create creating these kinds of problems
in the country in a very short time so
every session lasts only 45 minutes and
during this time we recreate the
scenario and try to like every group
because we work in pairs tries to kind
of go through this and because of this
after this 45 minutes we have a lot of
different experience for every session
and then we share so after 45 minutes
after every session we have a shot
retrospective where we share all our
insights and how we approach this
problem how are we what was challenging
what we have learned and through this
basically you share all the knowledge
you have explore new ways of doing stuff
and this is how you actually build up
new knowledge and I mean is a facility I
have quite some experience I guess that
probably over a thousand attendees in my
college which already so I've seen like
a lot of problems a lot of approaches so
I have like some ideas in which
direction to go so this is how I
structure the sessions but most
important for me is actually what
happens so basically react into every
session so once you're on a session you
see a problem or you see that a lot of
people have the problems and you try to
make the next session appealing for this
so you kind of try to work on the
problem okay so you said that it's
important to reflect them to do those
retrospective and you also said that the
next session might take into account
what you've seen in the session before
can you explain that in a little bit
more detail I mean you said that it's
game of life can you give an example of
how that didn't really work and how you
changed the example to emphasize a
certain point or something like that
mmm mother I don't know two questions
the first one was how do I choose the
next session another was how they alter
the rules of game of life actually I was
just trying to say but what you said is
that you would just implement game of
life and I'm not sure how you can
actually change sessions them because I
mean at the end of the day it's just
game of life and that's okay so you know
the funny thing is so first of all we
all do TDD and we do pair programming
and how we try to apply the follows of
simple design
so basically resolves this constraints
you cannot get it done in 45 minutes and
this is like I don't know by now ten
thousands of coded reads have been run
and nobody has finished that so you do
test-driven development so that means
that you write the test first and then
you do exactly sorry first rather it's a
test then you implement a continual
factor and this is because you want to
practice you know this is the time we
take away so your purpose practicing and
we really paying attention to the small
details and therefore therefore we never
actually depends kind of what kind of
session yet but you have to choose and
the aspect of the game you want to go
into and then you pay attention maybe
find sense to names because we do a
session without talking or we do a
session where you have where we play
ping pong so you switch do I have an
aggravator quite frequently so you have
to improve your pepper gaming skills how
we do a baby step session where you have
to conduct a green refactor cycle within
two minutes so you have to take smaller
steps and this is for instance something
I do when people tend to spend like 10
minutes for writing one test
yeah and depending on this I choose the
follow-up session so it kind of it's
coherent with ok so you introduce things
like baby steps to focus on specific
things like really going in in small
steps I see one thing that I'm always
wondering is I do believe the code
reviews are very efficient for
programmers to learn however quite a few
programmers don't know about history
from development for example so how do
we deal with that I mean I guess it's
not enough to tell those attendees well
we are going to do test-driven
development and that's it when they've
never done it before and I think it's
still like a complex in concept grasp I
mean the rules are quite simple the
problem is you have to have a lot of
practice so what happens usually like
every court we tested with your
introduction and I explained test-driven
development in let's it was women like
in a few minutes often with the help
from the audience and then we just apply
it and why this session is going on I
you know go around and
advice on this I like to challenge
people and confront them with that
they're not doing it in dr and so's idea
that can improve on it so they have a
shorter feedback okay so do you think
it's more important to actually talk to
those people during the session or is it
more important to do the retrospective
after the session it depends so I think
that the retrospective is more important
like that's difficult to say what is
more important
I'd say the disrespect if you have to do
any how and it's really important so
that people can synchronize and see what
does I have done or what others have
done talking to specific pairs during
this session is kind of also limited to
how many facilitators and how many
attendees you have I guess I can maybe
talk and let's say four or five pairs
during a session because often I want to
have a follow-up so I go to prepare and
see there is something you know a kind
of problem both test is to make out said
like the test name is telling something
else and that test implementation or
they don't get they don't make progress
and since I you know asking some
questions and then couple minutes later
I come back and come see what kind of
progress they made and can then
intervene and ask more questions so what
you do a code retreat with just one
facilitator or but you have multiple
well I started doing this doing this on
my own son like with one facilitator and
you can definitely do this and there's
like no more you cannot do this and
actually if you go to code retreat org
you will see that there are two roles
and host and a facilitator and there's
one facilitate nevertheless from my own
experience running a code retreat it was
over 40 people and being the only single
facilitator just exhausting so it just
drains my energy and therefore nowadays
I always prefer to do this with multiple
facilitators if possible okay because
then you didn't have have better energy
throughout the day because you can just
rechargable between as a facility as
well you just mentioned the host seems
to be a different role so what's the
difference between a facilitator and the
host and
funny thing so it took me like two years
to understand this even so it's on code
retweet or talk well so there is
obviously some person who needs to take
care of the location because we need a
room
we need like chairs and tables for let's
say 20 30 40 people we need some
catering for them so we usually start
with a breakfast so that's like kind of
an icebreaker and everybody can
introduce and also then we have tons and
all these stuff
somebody needs to handle with that and I
used to do this like in one rule and was
really exhausting so now nowadays I
always want to have a fan
somebody host who is single
responsibility for the location and
everything which is involved in that
also power you know sometimes what power
doesn't work I had to actually a couple
of times so that the Wi-Fi doesn't work
like a lot of weird things yeah and you
don't want to be also involved in this
when you even use a facilitator also
when people arrive they will not arrive
at the same time so they were like you
have a stream of people and just to make
to create a really nice atmosphere safe
space it's always have to welcome every
one of them if it's okay and that's
really nice if you have somebody who is
just annoying inviting people to come in
and show them around and stuff like this
and that's like very difficult to do
this in one person okay and the
facilitator is basically the one the
person who's running the event and after
each session you would throw away the
code why is that I mean this is
obviously not how we do it in the
industry in general right well I guess a
lot of people would like to do that I
mean now how so this is actually the
icebreaker often Muse you know how I ask
people how often would you like to throw
out some code we have written sometime
before you just inherited from somebody
and I mean people are like people who
are new to the concept of course
retreats are kind of frustrated in the
beginning because you know the said I
was so close to getting this done and
they have still this metaphor of the
getting things done instead of
practicing and improving
and I just imagine if we would keep the
code which you might do if you like do
joint sessions which sometimes uses like
two sessions on some cool piece or
something
but in general we throw the code away so
if you wouldn't do this people would
stick to one idea and they would like
for the whole day they choose one pass
and the blindly will follow will try to
follow this path what I want to achieve
and what's the idea of code retreat is
to explore different passes different
possibilities therefore you get more
benefits in my opinion if you explore
like six different approaches six
different paths because then you can
compare and then you get like ideas how
you could use these things and this is
why we throw this away okay I see makes
make sense also you said before the show
that quad retreats are a safe space so
can you elaborate on that yeah so I also
work with a lot of development teams and
I have like this two perspective having
a code retreat and having maybe a normal
workshop or working with developers and
I see often like people are afraid to
ask questions you know they think you
know I cannot ask is how to implement
this here because it will expose me as
somebody who doesn't know something and
you're just ashamed or afraid or
whatever and we don't know we want to
create a safe space where it's okay to
ask every single question because and
also to expose your weaknesses and the
missing knowledge if everybody has as I
have this as well so when we have the
situation where it's okay to not know
something then it's much easier to share
ideas to share approaches to share
knowledge and this is where we just why
we try to create this kind of
environment where people don't say you
know you don't know anything and we're
not who code with you because I will not
learn something from that and I strongly
believe that no matter what kind of
spirits you have you always learn
something that and sometimes senior
people believe you know everything and
they all all about TDD and then all
software design but once they try to
explain this to
somebody who's maybe neutral in the
stream they will just discover you know
that okay dislike maybe some flaws even
reflect on your habits because we tend
to assume wants to choose a weight of
doing things and keep with that and so
you have some habits as a developer and
this is like the also the challenge to
reflect on your habits and I mean I
agree it's even as a senior I think you
can take away quite a few things from
those khodro treats would you rather do
a code retreat with just one language
like I don't know JavaScript or Java or
well how do you do it is is it rather
that you say okay anyone can come and
then you just have a lot of different
developers with a lot of different
backgrounds what do you think which
approaches the better one
I mean the call it would start it
originally as a single language event
because at that time and 2009 when
Korean started it I think people could
not imagine how this is going to work
with like other people with different
developers this enterprise Java guys and
this you know start up Ruby JavaScript
guys and then also for me it was kind of
difficult to to imagine how this works
yeah but later on the people just
discovered H it's quite difficult to set
up a single language event nowadays okay
so just on just out of this because they
were like people with different
languages and you could not find like
easier to find just developers and
developers of a particular language who
have time and who want to come so like
both become brothers here who brought to
contribute to Europe she started this
multi-language event and it's kind of
stick to that so now you have this also
I started when I started we basically
had already multi-language events and I
think this is like really beneficial
even though it may sound scary and
confusing I think this is a really
really good idea to do that how would
that work
I mean me as a Java developer would I
only pair with other Java developers or
am I suppose to join other developers or
what's what's the idea there what I
usually do like when
an introduction of the coated read I
asked people to show hints and look
around what kind of languages we brought
there and you have like really used
careful language sometimes we have even
COBOL there ya know and I've seen people
find doing Co bouillon and I really
encourage people to try out a different
language may be more functional language
or like weak or strong type language
because just to see the differences just
to see where is like the strong was the
strongest of this language was would
maybe benefit nowadays there was there
are not a lot of developers I see who
only work with one language and as I
didn't see this like for years the
project have been and what I always well
even before the court agrees I just
always thought you know why is this so
easy in this language and why is it so
difficult in why my language and I
always try to make this work in my
language and this brought me to try out
different approaches and I find this
very beneficial to just challenge
yourself and ask you this cannot be so
difficult in my environment my
frameworks my language why is it so easy
with this environment and then okay you
try to make it work or you maybe switch
the images try something else yeah I
mean one of the sessions that I attended
here with with the pair was we I
basically tried to develop the stuff in
a purely functional manner in Scala and
that was quite educational for me so
that was quite interesting so how do you
create those pairs I mean you already
said that there are limits concerning
the languages so how do you set them up
yeah okay well actually chooses by
themselves usually so you know people
ask around they maybe want to pair with
somebody because they want to try out a
language on a new sample this is the -
usually nevertheless what I most of the
cases I start the first session the way
that I better continue like a scale
where people are sorting themselves by a
certain skill so often by Greenfield
code retreat it would be test-driven
development experience so you line them
up by the experience they have with
test-driven development
and then you you try to have same
experience in one team or well I try to
give them like the people who have want
to learn a lot their boost so i pair
them with the most experienced ones okay
I see so this is how we get this like
really fast going okay and then they
would learn from one another
mmm what do you think what why why would
I participate in any code retreat for
this like the major reason why I would
do it that's tricky
yeah so why would you do this I mean
usually they're like well they are
public and closed code retreats but
let's assume like the public ones they
usually take place on Saturdays
so you need to like take a day off kind
of take a day off from your family in
causes so you have to really want that
yeah and it's a whole day and we start
early so we start 8:30 but you could
change that right I mean you could do
code retreat on just a normal working
day and you know started at a normal
time that what is the normal time yeah
well I would argue depends on on Berlin
so maybe in Berlin it's more like 10
o'clock nevertheless we start in Berlin
at 9:00 so and I just I know I remember
the first coded with you know a bill and
I started at 8:00 it was like crazy yeah
but still I mean why do why do you do
that it seems that you are that you're
intentionally making the code which
treats less attractive right this is
kind of a tradition so it was this like
this all the time and I think there are
like two two reasons for this like one
is you have like a lot of stuffs you
have six sessions you know with respect
if you have a final retrospective
introduction if lunch so you really need
about eight to nine hours for that and
one thing the other thing is you
actually want the commitment of people
so you want them to be a relief because
they really want that there's a need to
show that they want that so this is kind
of tricky why people go to a coffee read
if they hear this may be the first time
they think well I have better things to
do on Saturday most people I get active
because of referrals from former
participants I have like most people
come because they've heard this is a
great event their colleagues have
learned a lot and was a lot of
and this is why they can't come all
people bring their colleagues I have
been to Accord retreat and say well come
with me I will this an amazing event so
if you if you talk about those
traditions or rules of code retreats it
sounds like you wouldn't do that as a
training event inside a company what do
you think I mean is it like this is the
way things should work and that's the
only way to do it or can you do
compromises are our compromises useful
concerning that I mean I in Germany at
least I think it's not even possible to
to have employees working on the weekend
without a very good reason
well first of all like the public core
itself of ways or just like opened area
you cannot charge anything for that or
you should not touch anything but just
like this period of the code retreat
nevertheless it's like ok to do also
close and retreats for companies and do
this quite a lot because people have
been to my public ones and I wanted to
have this was a development team inside
the company and obviously then it can be
maybe more specific to the company's own
I don't tend to change too much what I
sometimes to is that I run five instead
of six sessions so you still start a 8 o
clock just you start with with a
breakfast I try to do that in almost I
think in most cases we actually did this
like a public one so basically we
started back breakfast so I convince
people that it's good idea because often
we have people from different
departments even different locations so
just to get to know each other and also
for me this is like a great chance to
get the people to know and yes we might
cut down on one session or extend
session then what happens also sometimes
we
[Music]
longer introduction so I feel like
people from different parts of the
company so maybe we we do some some
exercise to introduce them to each other
okay
desperation the funny thing is with the
Saturday so even so you would say that
close caller treat would not happen on
Saturdays and I think most of my clothes
code return during the week nevertheless
I have a client where only to cover -
it's on a Saturday okay and this is they
do this on purpose because they want the
commitment of the people okay makes
sense but what you're saying is for a
close coach retreat for a company you
could actually change the rules well I
think I even got did public ones during
the week on Saturdays Sundays are just
like no code read police who would come
and arrest you but the funnies I mean
the funny the interesting thing is if we
do it on Saturday then you have also the
chance to have maybe a video link to a
different place on the world which is
which is also running quarterly so
instead of like a Code Red should every
Saturday a step what you're saying maybe
not every but like a lot of core
retreats happening on Saturdays and
because it's all over the world so
there's a really good chance that when
you do record it on Saturday there is
some other place on the world which is
also doing a concert read and how would
I find out about those coverage will
just go to court retreat dot org okay
and there you can see there's a calendar
with all the retreats and you've never
because you just mentioned that you
would you know create a video link there
is no such thing as a virtual code
review I guess like where you would just
meet in cyberspace I mean there are
tools for remote pair programming and
stuff so you could theoretically
probably do that well you could do is I
mean the benefit is already being
one-on-one with people
nevertheless they have been some cross
court retreat sessions so when some
there's one see it as probability of
court retreat we have like over 150
court reads at the same day so there are
like a lot of where a when is that that
global day of court retreat it's under
this year that's on the 14th of November
oh okay
so that this year's actually 2015 and I
guess for the other years I can find it
code receipt or doc you just go to GDC
r33 talk okay global day of cultural
trees okay got it
mmm so we already spoke of a public and
closed coach retreats I think you said
there are half public could retreats
what's that that's an interesting thing
so I did this for a couple of clients
and it was amazing event so instead of
so they wanted to do this for their
developers but they wanted to have also
some more because what makes what is the
difference between a great coach which
we done an amazing cotton trade I would
say this is like also having the right
people there okay and I think that every
code reviews a great event and because
justice structures the code really makes
it it just just flows I remember very
first college we didn't know anything
still was a great event but doing an
amazing so you not talking about the
facilitator but the people so you want
to expose people to different ideas and
different case of experience so this
client I have in mind so they had as I
convinced them to open this code repeat
as I did it for the company during the
week but like a third of the places was
open for public so I could invite my
friend from the software craftsman ship
community to join me on this day and
they brought like a lot of ideas and a
lot of knowledge this is I think the
first time that we we are mentioning the
word software craftsmanship so can you
talk a little bit about that yeah so
this is AG how I started I was cold feet
so I am there was this in 2011 I guess
the first some kata the first software
and craftsmanship testing conference in
Germany and we did it like kind of a
savory treats on matinee in the woods
for two and a half days and spend a lot
of time discussing software
craftsmanship topics and out of this the
the in Germany we found it's a soft wax
camera which is like an organization
where local groups organize each other
and I started a small local group in
Sissoko mob min stars number pediafed in
it mmm and the eyes and we didn't have
anybody's as I started to run e-coat
retreats just recruit people who's our
group and so I got started with this and
then you can say what is software
craftsmanship about it like different
opinions my opinion is a little bit
counter movement or an extension to the
agile movement so we have to search our
manifesto which is already quite older
and then couple years ago we had
software craftsmanship manifest so and I
think that this is like a counter
movement to pay more in tension also and
the practices we as developers should do
it focused a lot on coding like in the
how it is done but for me it's extends
to why more so it's like I see this as a
holistic view on software development so
everything you need to get involved in
this it's also getting the ideas right
understanding the business and providing
a great user experience at the psyche
but there was less we practice so like
one of our rules is practice and share
so we share in practice during the code
retreats therefore we run a lot of
culture treats inside the software
craftsmanship groups just out of
curiosity I mean there is this book
called software craftsmanship that is
not like the foundation of the software
craftsmanship community that you're
talking about it seems because you were
a French net otherwise or like this is
like this is also what do you understand
in this in this is like remembered say
she does a topic so we already spoke
about well close some haptic code
retreats there are also cultural suites
that are different concerning what you
actually cover so maybe we want to talk
about that too there are code rich it's
like I don't know the legacy code should
test automation code retreats what are
those about because you you know you
said that it's all about just creating
game of life and obviously game of life
is not like your legacy code base well
you could do this actually so during a
normal call you treat people like with
two green for development nevertheless
so I often do a joint session where I
make people create crap code in 25
minutes and then another group needs to
clean this up
so you can get some legacy involved in
this nevertheless there is for instance
this legacy code retweets which have
been brought to us by the tribunes
program today you have already code base
and you start working on this existing
crappy code base and try to write tests
for this and explore this and maybe
improve it and it's really interesting
so I find this concept of code retreat
quite intensive and challenging so I
love legacy code retreats nevertheless I
encourage people to join if you could
read normal code reviews before going
like a sinkhole to trees because then
it's like even more stuff okay because
we do everything we did in the ecology
but then then we also have to deal with
legacy code and and we try different
strategies to get this somehow our
control
okay so legacy code retreats what about
test automation or you know this was an
idea by Markus caetna and this is quite
interesting as well so starting like you
have a code base and you don't just a
sauce like a seam we have a web
application for instance and you want to
write some acceptance tests for this and
I am I ran a quite a few of them and
it's really interesting because so you
have a cold place and you try it out the
two different ways of writing acceptance
test for this and if anything is what I
like the ultimate of goal and sometimes
you succeed with this and then this
actually so that you start all with the
code base we were snow snow sources you
can just access it maybe why I am HTTP
right acceptance test which covers the
domain and once you do this you throw
out the code base and write a new code
to the acceptance that you have written
and you actually do that like in in one
day yeah that is really challenging so
but but it can be done I've seen this a
couple of times at it so sometimes I do
this like four five session and there's
six sessions they were really good and
have still energy we write our own code
base against the test cases we have
created
okay say anything else I mean legacy
test automation any other types of coral
sheets that you know about you know like
that different retreats but in this area
I'm not aware of any what are other
Retreat types of retreats yes or death
like all those my friends is a coaching
retreat oh okay so more like completely
different subjects we already spoke
about the example which it seems
obviously game of life and you made a
point that it makes a lot of sense to
try it over and over again do you ever
use different examples does that make
sense or is it that always game of life
legacy code retreat I sometimes use even
code bases from clients that's not
interesting if I like a close one and
the normal calls retweet I actually I
think I tried once a different cutter
but I I always use game of art because
can be explained very very easy and two
three minutes you can explain it you can
draw it it's easy it's easy to
understand but its case very well so
this is you can add so much complexity
to it so if you have people I have
people who have been mad over them ten
code retreats of mine and they say okay
I've done this many times this game so I
can give them additional rules so
expenses a space for instance do it like
in three dimensional four dimensions or
do stuff which add mules for instance on
bit cells which oneself dies and we we
bonus some bit cells and they will kill
all the cells around them I stuff like
this so you can easily adapt system to
make it more challenging one thing that
you just mentioned shortly you said that
you're actually using client code bases
in legacy code repeats so what I
actually get like a better structured
code base after such a legacy code
retreat that I can use some production
that is and is easier to modify
afterwards I find this quite difficult
so what I did a couple of times I'd like
to say for the first four sessions we
use this example code pace and then we
maybe
tried one particular class on one party
area of the code base and then moldy
cheese repairs were working on this and
after this they had something they could
maybe spend a little more time and but
they explored different ways or to
handle this and this was actually
interesting I had well I'm not like this
is challenging you go because client
code bases are used so you have ready to
prepare this well and I don't do this
often but I did it one time one time I
did it there was that there were two
teams and the two teams had to work on
the other teams corpus
I was really interesting okay like the
code base that they during normal days
work on or like what you created in the
culture tree
so it was like sent some dependencies
but says it was code bases and just to
understand the other side and but I find
it's really difficult because real code
bases are huge and you learn a lot of
justice just an example code base which
is which is only a few hundred lines oh
I agree I think even for the DC code
retreat it's still true that you learn
some pretty nice techniques and actually
apply them in factors so we spoke
shortly about constraints so I want to
dive deeper into that and you said that
for example you could put an emphasis on
naming or you could have this ping-pong
thing I know for example that there is a
constraint that says one writes the test
the other one writes the implementation
is what kind of constraints are there
and how do they work and and how
important are they and other a like any
constraints that you would use quite
frequently well I guess the sky is the
limit here so there are a ton of
constraints so you can make up
constraints really easy I have a list of
over 70 constraints there was some which
I used frequently so for instance like
ping-pong to encourage more sharing more
pair programming baby steps to encourage
smaller steps so let's talk about income
for minutes so how does it work
so Dybdahl survivor
relations on this like the easy one is
that the first one starts writing the
test then you switch the next one
implements refactor and write the next
test and then you switch again and then
so it's always implementation test for
the other one and so on and so on okay
so this would could be one thing also
you could do this that one person only
writes tests as a only writes
implementation you can in my opinion you
can nearly simulate every problem you
have in software development in this 45
minutes okay all right like a hand over
so you can maybe do something like a
rotating dojo that you kind of like
playing chess and power unit so you work
you you rotate on let's say four or five
different code bases and you see how's
this for different code bases are
involving with other people and get
involved in this
oh so you would rotate one part of the
pair and rotate them and you would do
that in one session or what you rotate
them session after session and keep the
code this is like there are also the
constraints which go over to sessions
this was a rotating you can do this in
one session so how does it work I mean a
sessions 45 minutes if I understand
correctly so I would just work for 10
minutes or with one parent and switch
over to the next yeah okay so like maybe
five or seven minutes so daya I always
try to depends also very much on the
audience if you have a very experienced
on the inside also runs the code Twitter
to sakata's conference where all like a
lot of facilitators are kind of a quiet
experienced audience so we can like to
push there a little bit harder and do
more challenging constraints and there
you we can try to alter like the
craziest and the interesting things of
versus rotations is just an example of
like a ton of others the interesting
thing is you have an idea about your
code pieces starting this and then you
see how other people got involved and
like got your ideas totally wrong and I
saw this in other directions and and
this is like really like handover yeah
or you get copies from somebody and
there are no tests or you get only the
tests from the previous session and no
code base and you have to write the code
for which passes the test are you you
can also introduce late requirements and
I was just saying you know and now you
have to I don't know a different space
you don't have a diversity of like I
don't know six
whatever you have three dimensions um
the time is taking different and like
that's the only limit is our imagination
and it's the basic idea of a quarter
twist basically push you and challenge
the attendees to explore new ways and
get like newer explore the horizont of
possible solutions okay sounds like a
lot of fun so what do you think what's
the effect of of coral shade so doesn't
make a developer actually a better
developer or it would it improve the
quality of the code after work what is
the experience I totally believe in that
so I really it sounds funny but I always
say you know better developers and when
you arrived here and I told you
convinced of that
because even I learned every time
something which I didn't see or learn
before yeah it's are there any like kind
of success stories that you could share
so I've seen like a couple people who
implemented ideas of a legacy code to
treat in the production code pace okay
so then even we did just like our
consulting companies and we did some
stuff we do in the legacy code which we
implement this in production code any
ideas what about those fundamental
things like a pair programming for
example I mean pay programming has been
wrong for a long long time and I don't
know what what your experience is like
but I still think it's adopted rather
slowly and in some cases it's not
adopted or also what about that do code
retreats help there of course I mean the
funny thing is I've seen this points
with clients they have teams and they
actually sitting sometimes next to each
other but they don't talk and during
this code retreat we mixed everybody
with everybody so you have to work with
people from other parts and then I've
seen this at for instance when a client
was working for there was really trouble
because people didn't communicate for
him well and actually after this coded
with totally changed because people were
working during this colloquy together
and had a lot of fun and learn from each
other
and then the communication afterwards
was much better I have sounds sounds
really great
so how can you get involved I mean
if I want to participate in the code
retreat how would I do it you already
mentioned code retreat or dark and that
there is a calendar that gives states of
code retreats any other ideas or
suggestions oh I could make it work for
me it's actually really easy you just go
to court through Tito org and everything
you need to know is explained there so
you can basically run it by yourself and
you can always ask like more experienced
facilitators to help you like Planeta
you how it works and we even preceding
the global day of code reach which we
have a lot of training sessions on skype
and hang out well experienced
facilitators teach other people how to
facilitate a country treat for free is
um yes so that's this library
community-driven think and of course you
can just look in the calendar and go to
Co treatment if it's near your place and
of course you can always invite an armed
facilitator to do this at your place or
at your company so this is like now you
can just invite people and usually a
fifth time they will do that what skills
would I need to participate in one
should I be annexed should I be like a
senior developer knows lot of languages
or should I be a junior or what's the
level that you're aiming at well I think
that all the people who are there are
the right people not just like this it's
really like their sense we do what like
we DVD versus experience we have and we
have a diverse experience every time and
so they're rich coated with this a
little bit different depending on the
people and I personally think that
they're really great for mixtures like
all different kinds of experience so
it's really beneficial to have a few
people who already know TDD ends of a
development well that it did helps but
it's not like must you already said that
at least during the global day of code
retreat
there are training sessions for posts if
I want to host a cultural trip by myself
of a third hip one how do I do that
I mean logistics no I mean like first of
all to me the question would be is there
any specific skill that I would need I
think that the format is amazing for the
helps you to deliver a great workshop
what is how I did it in Brittany stick
to the format don't think too much
choose the easy constraints like choose
something ping-pong baby steps really
easy stuff and once you get like more
familiar with format and get more
confidence than you cry and try out most
of what also helps is co-facilitating
you know inviting maybe more experienced
facilitator and do this with them
together all obviously go to a few
coders it's yourself before you try to
run on but I mean you said that it
should be fine to basically do it by
yourself and just start well it would
work yeah I would advise to at least
talk to experienced facilitator and
asked him for some advices and I do this
what people ask me and I have time so I
can I've you know I I did a lot of
training sessions also and people you
know and I've done I have done and can
call me and we can discuss this and
because the day it helps you know there
was like a lot of things which I could
talk for hours about like some details
and some stuff and how you structures is
how it was in introduction so what a
good use good metaphors be like
inclusive with people don't judge so
much you know how do you do the
retrospective and stuff like this is
there like any books or like a manual
that says how you would run it not yet I
was actually you know if I would have
only more time yeah okay I think that's
quite a common problem it's kind of a
man to do this somewhere so you just
said that you would be happy to help
people they want to run a code retreat
by themselves so how would they contact
you or what I how would I get in in
touch with other facilities I guess you
can't really do all these code retreats
just by yourself or help all those
facilitators just by yourself well yeah
like a lot of experienced facilitators
when friends and odd eunbong baku you
can just go to court vetoed organ see
who has a lot of events for instance if
you want to get in touch with me just
tell me on twitter yeah at martin closer
I'd rather drop me an email on a martini
at closer brothers dotty so we'll put
that in the show notes - if you're ever
in Berlin and we have like an amazing
software craftsmanship group here and we
do a lot of code if it's a also welcome
to drop by and then we can also talk
about this and it's in English right I
mean the yeah of course like Berlin is
really cool yeah
Bern is really international what are
your highlights about cockroaches what
is it that you like best about all of
that I think that like this a highlight
in every single one of them so I should
try to give to the most interesting part
so from it's like a workout so it's like
you really want out after this and this
is like you know this is like you push
people to the limit and you explore
really the limits this so it's
exhausting kind of and this is a good
thing about it's like a good workout and
then other thing is like maybe two
interesting stories from from cause
retreats so I remember this I think it
was my very first one of the my first
retreat and I was in an area where
basically no community was going on
there were like only two user groups
which didn't talk to each other and I
was so desperate so that I printed out
fires and went around from company and
knocking on doors and giving them flyers
- for the first code retreat and at one
company like the lady at the front desk
she said yeah but our developers it is
so good they don't need to learn
anything anymore
okay and she's basically rejected me and
okay and funny so somehow one of this
amazing developers arrived at our event
from this company I don't know how he
got noticed about it but he arrived and
he was it for the whole day and in the
final retrospective you asked people
what they wanted to try out different
when they come back to you to work and
he said well I want I don't want to get
back to work because it sucks so much
and I would like to be in a company
which I would just pair programming
tester in development and we're coding
actually makes fun that was like an
interesting thing when
I think story was I once did a half
public court retreat and if anything is
that they were two developers who
arrived and they said yeah after the
introduction yet well this event is kind
of not for us because we're doing these
programming languages and all the other
people are doing different programming
languages and they actually wanted to
leave I I have this sometimes people
want to leave really yeah even in public
culture sometimes people so for instance
this happens sometimes to juniors so
they are like afraid to expose and this
is like do you need to create a safe
environment and just invite them all or
find nice pairing buddy for them and
they stay and most people stay then the
whole day and with these two guys I was
able to convince him to stay for was it
wanted to leave but they had a problem
at hand
so they had like something in the coal
piece they were working on and likely or
funny this just a couple days before a
long-running workshop on that kind of
technology so I was able to give them
some hints but I only gave him so many
hints that they stayed for one session
and after that sessions I wanted to
leave so after that session I give him
another few breadcrumbs so that we
welder state and like every style
session they wanted to leave and it just
gives them enough information so that
rather state and after this six sessions
is they said he said you know you guys
had so much fun you learn so much new
things and we only solved our problem
and this is like what's really the key
point of code retreat it's not getting
things done but actually explore new
things and have fun and learn so they
really worked on problem at hand yeah
figured out later on that they really
should actually waste at the time
because the problem they could have
solved any other day and there was like
the chance to learn from other people
and they missed out on this yeah
anything else you want to tell our
listeners and any like final words that
you want to say I think it's an amazing
event accorded it so you get hooked I
mean that's once you start with this you
cannot stop so I really recommend this
to everybody and especially if you see
that
you have like shortcomings and your
development skills or the team and you
want to explore new ideas then then
bring your colleagues around the reason
why I wanted to do that show is because
to me it's an ongoing question in
particular about test-driven development
for example the original article about
test-driven development said that I
think was J unit test infected
programmers love writing test or
something like that I see too little of
that in our industry so I think a lot of
people are not just infected and from
all the things that I know like
trainings and coaching and stuff it
seems that the code retreats are the
most efficient way to teach people at
least about TDD and probably will
associate technical techniques like
refactoring and so on so I would
certainly second that it's a it's a very
good way not to just have fun but also
to educate about development I just
wanted to thank the amazing team behind
globally of code retreat who made this
great event happening so it's Jim Hardy
babaco and then I uncover even coos on
each and Panji thank you a lot guys and
keep on rockin excellent so thanks for
for being on the show thank you for
having me
and yeah you'll find a lot of other
information in the show notes and I hope
you enjoyed listening to this show thank
you thanks for listening SC radio an
educational program brought to you by I
Triple E software magazine for more
information about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website @ SC -
radioman to provide feedback you can
write comments on each episode on the
website or write a review on itunes
mention a message us on twitter at SC
radio or search for the software
engineering radio group on
Google+ or Facebook you can also email
us at team at se - radio net this and
all other episodes of SU radio is
licensed under the creative commons 2.5
license thanks again for your support
[Applause]
[Music]
you